- Hey, Jane.
- Got a positive I.D. on the victim.
Viktor Mendelssohn, 62.
He was a diamond cutter.
He has a shop
in the San Francisco Diamond district.
Same as it ever was...
more bodies, more death.
Not exactly the same.
This one was eviscerated
with an electric rotary saw.
Excuse me.
Your toe.
Careful.
Sorry.
Is it me, or does Jane seem
a little bit off
since the feds took Lorelei?
Well, he spent six months
setting a trap for Red John.
He has nothing to show for it.
How would you feel?
Maybe we should invite him out
for a night with the boys.
All right, you ask him.
Well, I-I came out this morning
to snip my herbs.
It's always best to do that
right after
the morning dew evaporates.
And when I didn't see Viktor
I got a really bad feeling.
Do you usually see him
in the morning?
Every morning.
We chat over the fence.
Hey. Jane, this is Betty Fulford.
- Hey.
- She lives next door.
Patrick Jane.
So did Viktor tell you about anybody
who might wanna hurt him?
No!
Although... last night
when I was getting ready for bed
I did hear him arguing
with a man in his house.
- What were they arguing about?
- Flowers.
Really?
Blue orchids, to be exact.
They... they were shouting,
and Viktor never shouts.
And you were in your bedroom
at this time?
That's right. That's right.
My window was open.
Did you happen to catch a glimpse
of the other man?
Well, I tried to snoop, but I couldn't
see into the kitchen.
That's where they were
having it out.
What's that noise?
I have absolutely no idea,
but I will investigate.
- Everything okay in there?
- "Everything's fine!"
It's all peachy.
What are you doing in there?
Rabbit stew.
Yummy.
We need to fatten you up.
Come on, fella.
Hello.
What time did you get
to the house this morning?
Same time every Monday.
8:30.
I walk from the bus stop.
Do you have a key
to the house?
No. Mr. Mendelssohn
let me in.
But this morning
he didn't answer the door,
so I looked in the window.
Well, you did the right thing.
Calling the police...
very brave. Very brave.
I told Mr. Mendelssohn
something bad was coming
but he didn't listen to me.
Why did you think something bad
was on its way?
The black ants.
For two weeks I come now
and I clean black ants
from the house.
Black ants?
In some South American countries
it's said that if black ants
enter your house
then someone in your family
might die.
- You understand.
- "Si."
This is... an eagle's claw.
It will help you find
who did this.
Take it, please.
Okay. Thank you.
I will. I'll just...
Ooh. Oops. Excuse me.
Bunny?
Where's the bunny?
Here. Rigsby, hold this.
Has anyone seen a rabbit
around here?
Excuse me. Uh, did you happen
to see a rabbit?
Yeah.
Thank you.
Hello, fella.
Yeah?
There...
Ahh, there you are. Huh?
Gotcha.
You found him.
I take it this belongs to you.
Yeah. It's the third time
he's escaped.
Chews through that metal
like a floppy-eared rat.
- Thanks for finding him.
- Oh.
Pleasure.
Certainly took your time
getting here.
You were expecting me?
Yeah, of course.
You know something
about the murder?
Yeah.
Poor old Mr. Mendelssohn.
You know anything
that could help us?
You tell me.
How can I know what you know?
How can I know what I know
will help you?
You're testing me.
Why?
You don't have issues
with authority figures.
You know you're the smartest person
in most rooms.
What's your name?
Am I required to tell you?
Well, I'm just a consultant.
You don't have to tell me anything.
Then I won't.
Okay. Have it your way.
- Wait. Where are you going?
- Well, you're playing me.
You don't have anything helpful
to offer me.
Stop.
Who's playing who?
You think you can manipulate me
with reverse psychology?
Seems to be working.
Well, it's not.
I'll help you.
But not because of your lame attempt
to prey on my ego.
I'm bored.
Not a whole lot's going on
in my world.
And what world's that?
Come on.
Mr. Mendelssohn hardly went to
his store in the diamond district.
He, um...
liked to work close
to home here.
This is his workshop.
Have you been inside before?
No. But I've seen him go in a lot.
He spent all of his time here.
Wow.
This place is so cool.
Weird... is what it is.
It's like a place in a dream.
Close, but no cigar.
You're getting warmer, though.
What?
Who are you?
What's your name?
Here we go again
with the name.
You have a definite tendency
to obsess.
- Do people ever tell you that?
- All the time.
What are you hiding?
You tell me.
You're the mentalist.
I never said I was a mentalist.
Spooky.
So how did I know?
You're playing a little game with me
and I wanna know why.
Who are you?
What's your name?
- Charlotte.
- Okay. Well, that's half a name.
It's a start.
Half a nice name.
I had a daughter
named Charlotte.
I know.
No.
No, you don't.
Who put you up to this?
Red John?
Red John, Red John, Red John.
I am so over Red John.
You're not my daughter.
My daughter was murdered.
I found her body.
"You are safe, you are loved"
"and you are wise."
Who told you those words?
You did.
Every night
when you tucked me into bed.
Hey, Jane. How'd you find this place
before we did?
Lisbon, good. Uh, could you run
a background check on this girl?
She's playing a con on me.
A very good one.
And who are you, miss?
Hello. I'm his daughter...
Charlotte.
I've heard so much about you.
It's nice to meet you.
My daughter's dead!
- He's having another episode.
- Yeah.
Come on, buddy.
Why don't you have a seat?
- What is wrong with you?
- It's all right.
We'll explain it all to you.
We'll tell you everything.
Just sit down first.
No.
Charlotte's dead.
Everything okay in there?
What's going on?
Oh, my God!
- Did he ingest anything?
- Uh, tea. He... he drank hot tea.
- Hey.
- His heartbeat's irregular.
- Pupils dilated.
- Skin's unusually dry.
- Right here.
Get that to the lab!
In fact, extend the primary
crime scene into the kitchen.
No need for the lab.
It's belladonna, the devil's cherry.
I know it from working narcotics.
Belladonna's highly toxic.
That's why users dilute it
with tea.
The berries have
a sweet flavor.
They say it gives you
instant hallucinations.
Well, if the victim was tripping
it would make him a lot easier to kill.
- Is he gonna be okay?
- He's holding his own.
That's a good sign
but we need to get him to a hospital
- and pump his stomach.
- I'm gonna go with Jane.
Cho, you're in charge.
You two push on the investigation.
It's okay.
You know that Mendelssohn cut some
of the rarest stones of his time?
He was considered a master.
You have his client list?
Yeah, you should see this thing.
Leaders of industry, royalty,
Hollywood stars.
- Yeah, we need to run them down.
- I'm all over it.
I already have a call in to Clooney.
Preliminary forensics report.
There were no useable prints
on the teapot or bowl.
Well, except for Jane's prints.
Great. Smudging fingerprints,
drinking evidence...
he's like a drunk uncle.
What about the electric saw
that was used on the victim?
Two sets of prints.
One belongs to Mendelssohn
the other unidentified.
M.E. puts time of death
around midnight.
Now Lisbon said
the next-door neighbor
heard Mendelssohn arguing
with a man in his kitchen last night.
Did Mendelssohn live alone?
He was sharing his home
with his daughter Melaina.
Guess she hit hard times
last year and moved in.
She writes children's books.
- Where was she last night?
- Big Sur.
Rented a cabin to work on a book.
I notified her this morning.
She's driving home now.
Yeah. Definitely meet
with the daughter.
See if she knows who was
at the house last night.
- Right.
- Did the victim have any coworkers?
An assistant named
Julian Gallego.
Bring him in.
Let me know what you find.
Okay.
It's all right. I got it.
CBI.
Oh, yeah. Mr. Clooney.
Yeah, this is Agent Cho. I just have
a couple questions for you.
This way. This way, please.
- All right, we'll take it from here.
- Is he gonna be o...
Viktor was like Stradivari.
He could, uh, hear a flaw
in the diamond
by the way his grinding wheel
changed its song.
How long did you work
for him, Julian?
Four years.
Who's going to teach me now?
There is no one like Viktor.
When did you last see him?
Yesterday.
We spent the whole day
in the workshop together.
He was showing me
how to open a window.
A window?
Before making the first cut
Viktor would spend weeks
getting to know a rare gem.
You have to, uh, polish a window
in the cloudy surface
of the stone
so that you can peer
into its heart.
- Sounds romantic.
- It is.
A careless cut can shatter
your treasure.
Did your boss come into possession
of any rare gems lately?
Oh, yes.
A 102-carat blue diamond.
Most master cutters
will turn into old men
and... and never touch
a diamond over, uh, 50 carats.
100 carats? How much is something
like that worth?
Well, it's just a chunk
of rough crystal now
but after Viktor
was through with it...
$20 million.
And where is that diamond?
Viktor took it home with him.
He took all of his clients' stones
home with him at night.
He kept them close
in a...
hidden shoulder wallet.
There was no shoulder wallet
found on Viktor's body.
Did anyone have it in
for your boss?
Fahad. Fahad threatened him.
- Who's that?
- Fahad Ranjani.
Another diamond cutter.
Uh, minor talent.
The Blue Orchid
is a career-making stone.
Fahad thought it was going to him.
The Blue Orchid?
- Blue Orchid?
- That's right.
When was your last contact
with your father, Melaina?
Yesterday morning.
I-I called him from the cabin.
And he didn't indicate
that anything was wrong?
On the contrary.
He was so excited
about that new stone.
According to his
assistant Julian
he liked to hide his clients' gems
on his body?
Dad never took off
that beat-up shoulder pouch.
Even in bed.
Drove mom crazy.
And why would he do that?
He was raised not to trust
security services.
His father
was a German Jew who...
survived the Holocaust
only to have the bank steal
the family money.
And did anyone other than you
and Julian
know about the shoulder pouch?
We're the only ones he trusted.
Melaina, are you a tea drinker?
I am.
We found a toxic substance
inside your teapot.
I don't know anything about that.
Excuse me for asking, but...
can anyone confirm that you
were in Big Sur last night?
No.
I rent a remote cabin for solitude.
Would you consent
to a forensics exam
and an examination
of your vehicle?
No.
I mean, go ahead.
Do whatever you need to.
You're not real.
You're an hallucination.
Depends on your point
of view, I suppose.
It's the only reality that I know.
How come I'm strapped down?
'Cause you are strapped down.
Yeah, they're pumping
your stomach right now.
Listen.
"Set suction at 125 intermittent."
"Check his I.V. and get an
electrolyte bag, just in case."
"Yes, doctor."
Well, how about that?
So...
you're my daughter.
Well, at least how I imagine
my daughter to be all grown up.
Do I meet your approval?
You're a bit lippy.
Yeah, I get that from you.
Yeah. Sorry.
Not really crazy about that.
Hey, you didn't exactly turn out
the way I expected, either.
What's that supposed to mean?
What happened to you?
I've been dead for ten years
and you're still stuck in neutral?
You have no life,
just this endless obsession.
Red John. Red John.
Mom would not be happy.
Well, my relationship
with your mother is, uh...
it's my business.
Show a little respect.
Hello, I'm a figment
of your imagination.
Show yourself some respect.
This is what I've been missing out
on for all these years?
When do you go
to college again?
Look at you. You can't even be real
with someone who doesn't even exist.
Does anyone know
who you are?
Yes.
Who?
Well, come on. Who?
Lisbon.
Hey.
Hey, Jane.
- Hey, I'm back.
- Yeah.
You're gonna be okay.
They pumped your stomach.
- You took some kind of...
- Hallucinogen.
Hallucinogen.
Was it in the tea?
Belladonna leaves.
The doctor says it could take
a few hours to leave your system.
You're gonna be okay, though.
You just need some rest.
Yeah.
How you feeling?
Parched. Really...
so thirsty.
Can you get me a little water?
Please, belladonna?
- I'll be right back.
- Okay. Bye-bye.
Ah, Jane.
Great park.
You're still here.
You're still tripping.
It would seem so.
You really shouldn't be driving.
And you especially should not
be driving an ambulance.
Oh, that's some strong tea.
Now you're stealing
an ambulance?
No. No, I'm just admiring
the interior.
Wicked G.P.S.
How much you think
one of these rigs goes for?
You need bed rest.
I need to go back
to the crime scene.
What's her story?
She have a boyfriend?
Be quiet.
- I didn't say anything.
- I was talking to the hallucination.
- In bed now.
- When I was in the victim's kitchen
I made a breakthrough
in the case.
At least I thought I did.
That's about when the wacky tea
kicked in.
Fine. I will have Van Pelt
come down here
with crime scene photos.
Not the same.
I have to be there.
Hallucinations are part
of the subconscious.
- Mine could be clues.
- We'll go when you're lucid.
Well, when I'm lucid,
I could forget everything.
But right now, let me tell you...
right now my visions
are very, very real!
In other words, you wanna use
drugs to solve a case.
Some great minds did their best
work on hallucinogens.
And now you have a great mind?
- I like her.
- Oh, yeah, funny. Double act, huh?
Jane. You're scaring me.
Teresa, you can call me Patrick.
Drugs is not the path
I would choose
but it's been chosen for me,
so I must stay the course.
Please, I implore you
take me back
to the crime scene.
The Maharaja of Jodhpur
owns the Blue Orchid.
His royal highness called personally
to inquire about my services.
The commission was mine...
until Viktor Mendelssohn used
his flashy credentials
to steal my job.
I was told you threatened Viktor.
- I did.
- Did you kill him, too?
Come again?
It means "barking dogs seldom bite".
If I intended to kill Viktor
I wouldn't broadcast
my intentions.
Well, things happen
in the heat of the moment.
Things we can't control.
Right before he was murdered
Viktor was overheard in his house
arguing with a man
about the Blue Orchid.
What can I say?
It wasn't me.
But you're a barking dog, Fahad.
You just said so yourself.
Were you barking
at Victor last night?
What do you want from me?
Do you want to arrest me?
Then arrest me!
If not, I'm going back to work!
What do you have to say to that?
You're a person of interest, Fahad.
Don't leave town
without notifying CBI.
Did that sound like the man
you heard yelling last night?
It might.
No, he didn't sound...
I don't think that was him.
The man I heard yelling
didn't have an accent like that.
Last thing I remember was admiring
this beautiful butterfly.
Right here.
Real or imagined?
Real, I think.
Then I heard a bang
in that pot there on the stove.
What was in the pot?
A rabbit.
Like that rabbit?
Yeah, just like that
but my rabbit was real,
with a diamond necklace.
That is some hallucinogen.
She's kinda cute.
- I mean, have you guys ever...
- You be quiet.
Pressing on
I carried the rabbit
to the foyer...
and it jumped from my hands
and hopped out the door.
Then I moved down
the walkway looking.
"Where's the bunny?
Here, little bunny, bunny."
And I went through
the gawking neighbors'
and across the street.
Right here, I met this lovely
Scandinavian couple
that spotted the rabbit
hopping up that path.
- They were Scandinavian?
- Yes.
It's a clue, right?
Scandinavia. Reindeer.
Reindeer, Christmas.
I might have just figured out that the killer
has a December birthday.
Did the couple you met
kinda look like them?
You must have walked by them
on your way to the backyard.
Classic.
Still waiting for the subconscious
clues to kick in, Jane.
They will. Follow me.
- This is wrong.
- What's wrong?
This yard's different.
In my hallucination,
this was a...
manicured garden with a...
- Look at that pool!
- thing and a...
This...
Okay, so tell me what happened
back here in your vision.
The water's great.
It's where I met Charlotte.
Charlotte?
My daughter.
- Is that who you've been talking to?
- Yes.
She here right now?
Yeah.
Wh-what is she doing?
She's doing the backstroke.
I taught her that.
Jane, maybe your subconscious
didn't send you any clues
from the crime scene.
Maybe it sent you
your daughter.
- Why?
- I don't know.
Can we go back
to the hospital now?
- Workshop.
- What?
Charlotte took me
to the diamond cutter's workshop.
Last stop, I promise.
If we don't find anything,
I will tuck myself into bed
- and sleep it off.
- I'm gonna hold you to that.
Hey.
You have a key?
Yeah, Mendelssohn's daughter
gave it to me.
She said her father's
workshop was, uh...
in the back here.
And who are you?
CBI. We're investigating
Viktor Mendelssohn's murder.
You're his assistant?
Julian Gallego.
Uh, I work here.
It's not what I imagined.
You mind
if we take a look around?
Not at all.
I'm just packing up. Please.
Thank you.
I like the other workshop better.
This is so dull.
Why do even work
for the CBI, anyway?
You know why.
To catch Red John.
Okay. Whatever.
What does that mean?
"Okay, whatever."
Well, to be honest, Dad your obsession's
a little creepy and weird, you know.
What?
I do it all for you.
And your mom.
Yeah.
And I hate to be the one
to break this to you, Dad but...
there's nothing
that you can do for us.
We don't give a damn
what happens to Red John.
I mean, we're dead.
Gone.
And you need to start dealing
with that.
I deal with that every day.
Maybe that's the problem.
Could you please move?
Don't roll your eyes at me.
Uh, you don't need to go in there.
That's, uh, just my stuff.
You found it.
You found the Blue Orchid.
Yes.
In your stuff.
What's a 20-million-dollar
missing diamond doing in your bag?
Viktor's daughter said he kept it
on his body at all times.
I-I don't know
how it got in there.
Wait, you're not accusing me?
Viktor's neighbor
said she heard a man
arguing with Viktor last night
about a diamond.
Was that man you, Julian?
No.
I mean... Okay, yes.
Um, I was there.
- So you lied to Agent Van Pelt?
- No.
She never directly asked me
if I was at Viktor's house last night.
- You should've told her.
- How would that have sounded?
That you fought
with your boss, drugged him
stole his client's diamonds,
and then killed him.
We had a creative argument
over how to shape this stone.
We're both artists, passionate.
I didn't kill Viktor.
I idolized him.
Turn around and put your hands
behind your head.
- What?
- Do it.
Hey!
Come here.
Well, that certainly was easy.
Yeah, you're just saying that
because I found the diamond.
You wish.
Come on.
All righty then.
It's been real.
Hang on. Where...
where are you going?
Hello, I'm practically
a grown woman.
I don't need to tell you
where I'm going.
No, yeah, I...
I-I know, but...
You're coming back.
I love you, Dad.
- Hey, Jane?
- No, not now.
Wait.
Julian's in holding.
The D.A. likes the case.
- Is Charlotte...
- Gone. Tea wore off.
Well, you were right.
Your hallucination led us
to the killer.
No, my imaginary daughter
was right.
It's all too easy.
What are you talking about?
Well, I've never been to that workshop.
I've never even met the apprentice.
How would I know he was stashing
stolen goods there?
Who cares?
You found the rock.
That doesn't mean
we found the killer.
We've got a match
for the second set of prints
on the murder weapon.
They belong to Julian.
Meh, you coppers
and your evidence.
You always let it
confuse everything.
Of course Julian's prints
are gonna be on his boss' tools.
They were master
and apprentice, right?
You're really serious about this?
Yes. There's something
I am not seeing.
Rigsby, where's that necklace?
What necklace?
The one I handed you from
the maid that found the body.
The gardener found the body.
Well...
That means I hallucinated the maid.
Why?
Send myself a message.
An eagle claw necklace.
What are eagles?
Don't answer that.
They're hunters in the sky
with excellent vision.
Just after I... poured the tea
I was looking through
the kitchen window
watching a butterfly
and I saw the bedroom
of that, uh, neighbor lady...
what was her name?
- Betty.
- Betty. Yes.
Her bedroom
was on the second floor
up high, with an eagle's view.
How do you know
it was her bedroom?
She had lace curtains
and blackout shades.
Betty told me
she couldn't see the kitchen
from her bedroom window.
She lied.
- Okay. Play it cool.
- Okay.
Hi!
How's the, uh, investigation going?
Well, to tell you the truth, uh...
we're a little stuck.
Oh. Well, if I can be
of any more help...
There's an idea.
Oh, uh, uh, would you like
to come inside?
Only if there's a cup
of tea involved.
I'd love a cup of tea.
- Sure. Come on.
- Oh, fantastic.
We're closing in on Viktor's killer
but before we make an arrest
we need to find
his client's diamonds.
The Blue Orchid. I've been following
the news all day.
Oh, no, w-we found that.
The... the Blue Orchid was hidden
in the, uh, bag of Viktor's apprentice.
- Oh, so you have your killer?
- No. We don't think so.
Uh, relax, I'll fix the tea.
Only a foolish killer
would keep the Blue Orchid.
It's hard to move such
a high-profile piece quietly.
Oh, I see.
A smart killer would use
the Blue Orchid
to frame an innocent man
for murder
and keep the small diamonds.
They're easier to fence
but still worth a couple million.
Does anyone want, uh, lemon
with their tea?
- Just, uh, top that up there.
- Thank you.
There's... there's just one thing
I don't understand.
Why don't you believe
that Julian killed Viktor?
Doesn't that make more sense
it's more plausible,
than somebody framing Julian?
Framing him was the easy part.
After Viktor was dead,
all the killer had to do
was take his keys,
drive to his workshop
and plant the Blue Orchid
in Julian's bag.
Well, if that was the easy part
what was the hard part?
Uh, gutting Viktor like a fish.
Oh, dear.
- What's wrong?
- Oh, my goodness!
Something is tickling
my toe... oh, there it...
Where did that... oh!
Where did that come from?
Uh, where did what
come from?
- The rabbit.
- What rabbit?
I have no idea.
The... the rabbit!
There's a rabbit right here
in my house!
Where did it come from?
What is wrong with you people?
Why are...
Oh, no.
Oh, my Lord.
Which... which tea did you serve me?
Oh, Lord. Oh, Lord.
Oh, Lord. Oh, my God.
No, no, no, no, no, no!
No, no, no.
I will not answer your questions.
I will not answer anything.
I will not tell you
what you wanna know.
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa,
whoa, whoa, whoa.
No. No, please.
Let me go.
- Let me go!
- What do you got there?
No! No, I need help!
- Please!
-Viktor's shoulder pouch.
No, I need medical help! Please!
I just drank some belladonna!
- I need help!
- You drank raspberry hibiscus.
Sweet like belladonna,
it doesn't pack the punch.
Believe me.
But the... but the...
the... the rabbit...
Local pet store.
You tricked me.
- Come on. Let's go.
- You tricked me.
Your finances are a mess, Betty.
The money from your late husband's
insurance policy, long gone.
You couldn't make
next month's rent.
2 million in stolen diamonds
would've kept you living
in style for a long time.
What was he thinking?
An old man walking around
with all those jewels?
He was begging for it.
How did you know
he carried them on him?
Oh, please,
I've known for years.
His... his... his kitchen window's right
across from my bedroom.
Every night
I would lie in bed thinking...
"How can I get my hands
on that pouch?"
The Blue Orchid
was your shot?
Oh, framing Julian was one of, like
a dozen plans I've had over the years.
The daughter was at the cabin
and when I saw the two of them
in the kitchen with that big rock
I knew it was now or never.
Once Julian left,
I just... I went on autopilot.
Where'd you get
the belladonna?
I've had it for months
for just such an occasion.
All I had to do was drop in
and offer him a pot of tea.
The hallucinations
made it easier to kill him?
That was the original plan.
But once I lifted
the diamonds off Viktor
it... it... it was
the craziest thing.
He became so delusional
I convinced him
to take his own life.
What do you mean?
How?
I told Viktor that the diamonds
were trapped in his stomach.